A Guide to the Papers of Calvert Walke Tazewell 1935-1994
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
The Papers of Calvert Walke Tazewell 1935-1994
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
MG 75
12 document cases, 5 linear feet
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of C.W. Tazewell, June 2000.
Biographical/Historical Information
Calvert Walke Tazewell was born in 1917 in Norfolk, Virginia. He was educated in public and private schools in Norfolk. He enlisted in the Army Air Corps in 1937 and received a commission while overseas in World War Two. During the war he received the Bronze Star Medal for his service in the China Campaign. He reached the rank of Lt. Colonel, serving in communications and electronics and as commanding officer. He retired from active duty in 1959.
After the military, he worked as Civil Defense Coordinator for Dade County Florida, taught Civil Defense courses, worked for the Florida State Board of Health, and the Health-Welfare-Recreation Planning Council after returning to Norfolk.
Tazewell founded the Norfolk Historical Society, a group dedicated to preserving all aspects of local history, in 1965. He served as its president for two terms, then as Executive Vice President. He was also a co-founder of the Virginia History Federation, an organization that sought to link all history related groups in Virginia. He served as the Federation's first president in 1969. Tazewell was the founder and director of the Hampton Roads Central Library, an internet digital library and archive from 1993-1997. He also operated the W. S. Dawson publishing company until 1997.
Scope and Content Information
The Tazewell collection includes materials dated from 1935 to 1994. It includes correspondence, newsletters, press releases, meeting reports, and other papers relating to the Norfolk Historical Society, Virginia History Federation and the Friends of the Boush-Tazewell-Waller House. Also included is research material related to various aspects of Norfolk history, and index cards of contacts and organizations.
Mr. Tazewell was given the papers of Philip Brower, former archivist at the Mac Arthur Memorial in Norfolk. These papers include biographical and genealogical material about General Douglas Mac Arthur, research material about Mac Arthur's presidential ambitions in 1952, and material related to the Memorial and archive.
Included as well in this collection are the papers from Lucile Pearce, who was involved with the Norfolk Historical Society and Boush-Tazewell-Waller house. Her papers include mementos from Maury High School in the 1930s, a scrapbook of ephemera from amateur musical performances and photographs.
Arrangement
Arrangement
The collection is organized alphabetically by topic with the exception of correspondence which is organized chronologically within the series.
Organization
This collection is divided into six series:
Series I: Norfolk Historical Society includes material dating from 1965 to 1997 with the bulk of the material dating between 1965 and 1968. This series includes business papers, correspondence, press releases and newsletters.
Series II: Virginia History Federation includes material dated from 1967 to 1992 with the bulk of the material from 1967 to 1970. This series includes business papers, grant proposals, correspondence, press releases, and copies of the Virginia Phoenix.
Series III: Norfolk History includes research material relating to Norfolk landmarks, residents and events. Included in this collection are drafts of some of Tazewell's historical writings.
Series IV: Boush-Tazewell-Waller House includes legal and business papers and correspondence of the Friends of the Boush-Tazewell-Waller House, Inc. There is also a report on the architecture and history of the house written by Lucile Pearce.
Series V: Papers of Philip Brower includes biographical and genealogical information about Douglas Mac Arthur, research materials regarding Mac Arthur's presidential ambitions in 1952, papers and correspondence dating from 1965 to 1993 regarding Mr. Brower's tenure as archivist at the Mac Arthur Memorial archive.
Series VI: Miscellaneous includes mementos of Maury High School from the 1930s given by Lucile Pearce to Tazewell, photos and other historical information not related to Norfolk, index cards containing addresses and other information.
Related Materials
C.W. Tazewell created a website containing local history and family information that can be found at http://www.marquiswhoswho.net/CSTAZEWELL
Contents List
- Norfolk Historical Society
  - Business
    - Board of Directors (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Contributions and Expenses (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Forms and Form Letters (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Meeting Reports- 1965, 1968 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Meetings (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Membership Drive (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Office Management, Procedures (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence
    - Not Dated (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1965 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
    - January-October 1966 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 10)
    - November-December 1966 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
    - National Historic Preservation, 1967 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 12)
    - January-March 1967 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 13)
    - April 1967 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 14)
    - May-June 1967 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 15)
    - July 1967 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 16)
    - September 1967 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 17)
    - October 1967 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 18)
    - November-December 1967 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 1968-1994 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 20)
    - E-mails and Memos to Members of the Norfolk Historical Society, 1997 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Fort Norfolk (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Fort Norfolk Courier and Update, 1992-1994 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Genealogical Bulletin (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 3)
    - History of NHS (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Invitations and Event Announcements, 1966-1981 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 5)
    - News Releases, 1966-1968 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Newsletter, 1965-1987 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Photographs of EXPO and Office (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Proposals (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Old Christ Church Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Save Old Christ Church Campaign, 1966-1967 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 12)
- Virginia History Federation
  - Business
    - Business Papers, Budget (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Constitution (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Forms, Brochures, Mailings (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Grant Applications (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Mailing Lists (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Meetings and Conferences (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Press Releases (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Proposals (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Purpose of Virginia History Federation (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence
    - Not Dated (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 22)
    - September 1967-August 1968 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 23)
    - October 1968 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 24)
    - November 1968 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 1)
    - December 1968 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 2)
    - January 1969 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 3)
    - February 1969 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 4)
    - March-June 1969 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 5)
    - July 1969 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 6)
    - August 1969 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 7)
    - September-December 1969 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 8)
    - 1970-1992 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Biography Committee (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Commissioning of the USS Richard L. Page (DEG-5) (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Historic Building Preservation (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Lineage Societies-Information and Correspondence (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Presentations/Speeches (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Travel Industry (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 17)
    - The Virginia Phoenix, 1968-1974 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 18)
- Norfolk History
  - Account of Life in Norfolk in the Late 18th Century by Mrs. Ritson (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 1)
  - American Friends of Lafayette (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "Ancient History of Norfolk in Ragtime" (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Berkley (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Bibliography Virginia State Library, Richmond, 1991 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Boush, John (will), 1790 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 6)
  - The Boush Plan, 1910 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Brannan Bible (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Chronology-Norfolk History (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Chrysler Library/Museum (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Crime History, Letters to Editor (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Genealogy (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 12)
  - German Club (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 13)
  - The Gimlets Bridge Club (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Glennan, Michael (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Graham School (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Grigsby, Hugh Blair (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Grigsby, Hugh Blair-Oration, 1831 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 18)
  - History of Norfolk (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Hope, James Barron (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Howard Association (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Leache, Irene (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous Articles (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Monday Club (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Negro Schools in Norfolk (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Newspaper Clippings Re: Norfolk & Residents (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Newspaper Clippings Re: Norfolk Landmarks (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Newspaper Clippings: Tidewater Landfalls (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Norfolk Academy (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Norfolk Bar (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Norfolk Beacon (Photocopies), 1831 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Norfolk City Council and Burning of Norfolk, 1776 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Norfolk History/Bibliography (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Norfolk Mace (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Norfolk Maps (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Norfolk Mayors (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Norfolk on the Web (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Norfolk Pamphlets (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Norfolk Parks (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Norfolk Post Office (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Norfolk Stone Bridge (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Norfolk Street Cars (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Norfolk Street Names (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Norfolk Tricentennial (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Ocean View (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Old House in Norfolk, Photos and Negatives (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 2)
  - "Poetical Picture of America" (photocopy), 1809 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Ragtime Drafts (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Raising the Merrimack & Congress (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Russian Visits to Norfolk (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 6)
  - St. Paul's Church (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Songs about Norfolk (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Squires, William (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Street Lights (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Union Occupation of Norfolk (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Viett, George (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Vignettes from the Shadows-Drafts (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Vignettes-Maps and Other Illustrations (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Virginian Pilot-75th Anniversary (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 15)
  - The Weisiger Family (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Samuel L. Wilson (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Yellow Fever in Norfolk, 1855 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 18)
- Boush-Tazewell-Waller House
  - Articles of Incorporation of Friends of the Boush-Tazewell-Waller House (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Board of Directors-Correspondence, 1983-1987 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Board of Directors-Lists and Miscellaneous (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Board of Directors-Meeting Minutes (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Draft of Report on BTW House by Lucille W. Pearce (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Report by Lucille W. Pearce (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Brochures (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 25)
  - By Laws (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Financial Reports (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Mailing List (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Newsletter: Tazewell Talk, 1979-1988, 1990 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Post Cards and Invitation Cards (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Proposal Re: Preserving Old Buildings (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Publicity: Newspaper Articles, Pamphlets (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Restoration (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Tazewell Hall (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Tazewell Library (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 9)
- Papers of Phillip Brower
  - 1952 Presidential Election
    - Articles Re: Election of 1952 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Book Chapter: "The Coming of Power: Critical Presidential Elections in American History" (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Book Chapter: "Eisenhower: Captive Hero" (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Book Chapter: "Political Misadventure" (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Footnotes/Draft: "Mac Arthur's Last Chance: His Presidential Ambitions," 1952 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Mac Arthur & Eisenhower (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Mac Arthur and the Presidency, 1948-1952 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Notes, 1952 Elections I (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Notes, 1952 Elections II (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Notes, 1952 Elections III (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Phillip La Follette Papers (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Presidency 1952 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Presidency 1952: Letters and Speeches (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Republican Convention, 1952 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Speaking Tour (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Speeches (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Mac Arthur: Miscellaneous Information
    - Book Chapter: "Six Presidents, Too Many Wars" (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Bonus March (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Book Chapter: "Franklin D. Roosevelt Launching the New Deal" (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Book Chapter: "A Long Row of Candles" (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Book Chapter: "The Mac Arthur Controversy" (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Certificate of Americanism (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 12)
    - "Darling Baby Girl" (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Mac Arthur Biographical Information (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Mac Arthur Genealogy (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Newspaper Clippings: 1964, 1968, 1982 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Notes, Bibliographical Re: Mac Arthur (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Notes: Japanese Repatriation & Philippine Invasion (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Notes: Mac Arthur Opinions (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Post War Mac Arthur Correspondence (copies) (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Pre World War II Mac Arthur Correspondence (copies) (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Mac Arthur Archives
    - Brower's Speeches (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1965-1971 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1972-1993 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous Papers (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Photographs (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Storage on Shelves (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Mac Arthur Memorial
    - Brochures (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Jean Mac Arthur (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Mac Arthur Memorial Foundation (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Brower-Personal
    - Correspondence, 1962-1979 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Mac Arthur Stamp (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous Papers (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 16)
- Miscellaneous
  - Lucille Pearce
    - "Frolics of 1935" (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Maury High School Class of 1939-Reunion Roster, Sorority, and Club Rosters (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Maury High School Graduation, June 1939 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Maury High School Football, Songs, and Cheers (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous Maury High School Mementos (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Norfolk Society of Arts (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Photos of Mrs. Pearce and Others, 1900-1950s (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Photos of Mrs. Pearce and Others, 1960s (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Scrapbook (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Other Miscellaneous
    - Autograph Book: WSYR Radio, 1922-1972 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 1)
    - 18th Century Legal Papers (Photocopies) (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 2)
    - "Facts about the Civil War" from the Stonewall Jackson Memorial (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 3)
    - "Henry Clay Cocharane, 1841-1947," Marine Corps Museum, Quantico, Virginia (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Historic Maps, Jamestown/Yorktown (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Literary Club (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Notes, Clippings, Drafts (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 9)
    - "Old Ironsides" Booklet and "Treasure Map" (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 10)
    - "Oral History and the Mythmakers"-Preservation Leaflet (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Other Groups/Organizations (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Photographs, December 24, 1967 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Postcards: General Longstreet's Headquarters, Gettysburg, Pennslylvania (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 14)
    - P.T. Boats/Lt. Snelling (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 15)
    - "The South and the Midwest: Maps and Plans" (Catalogue) (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 16)
    - "Virginia Credit Union League History," 1922-1954 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 17)
    - "Virginia Librarian" Vol. 16, Spring 1969 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 18)
    - "The Virginia Numismatist," November-December, 1967 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Women's Suffrage (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Index Cards (Box Box 12)